One way to change our genes is to make new ones,
توجد طريقة واحدة لتغيير جيناتنا وهي صنع جينات جديدة
as Craig Venter has so elegantly shown.
كما عرض كريج فينتر ببراعة قبل قليل
Another is to change our lifestyles.
الطريقة الأخرى هي تغيير نمط حياتنا
And what we're learning is how powerful and dynamic these changes can be,
وكما رأينا كم هو مؤثر ذلك التغيير
that you don't have to wait very long to see the benefits.
فأنت غير مضطر للإنتظار زمن طويل لرؤية النتيجة
When you eat healthier, manage stress, exercise and love more,
عندما تأكل طعام صحي وتتعامل مع الضغوط وتمارس الرياضة والحب
your brain actually gets more blood flow and more oxygen.
في الواقع ذلك يجعل دماغك يحصل على قدر أكبر من الدم والأوكسجين
But more than that, your brain gets measurably bigger.
لكن أكثر من ذلك، خلايا دماغك تزيد بشكل واضح
Things that were thought impossible just a few years ago
في السنوات القليلة الماضية كان هذا يعد مستحيلاً
can actually be measured now.
من الممكن قياسها حالياً
This was figured out by Robin Williams
إستنتج روبين ويليامز ذلك
a few years before the rest of us.
قبل عدة سنوات من بقيتنا
Now, there's some things that you can do
هذه بعض الأشياء التي تستطيع القيام بها
to make your brain grow new brain cells.
لتجعل دماغك يكسب خلايا جديدة
Some of my favorite things, like chocolate and tea, blueberries,
بعض أشيائي المفضلة كالشكولاته والشاي والتوت
alcohol in moderation, stress management
الكحول بإعتدال والتعامل مع الضغوط
and cannabinoids found in marijuana.
المواد الموجودة في الماريجوانا
I'm just the messenger.
أنا مجرد رسول
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What were we just talking about?
أين وصلنا ؟؟؟
And other things that can make it worse,
أشياء أخرى تجعله أسوء
that can cause you to lose brain cells.
وقد تسبب فقدان لخلايا الدماغ
The usual suspects, like saturated fat and sugar,
المتهمون عادة، مثل الدهون المشبعة والسكر
nicotine, opiates, cocaine, too much alcohol and chronic stress.
النيكوتين والأفيون والكوكايين والإفراط في الكحول باللإضافة للضغوط المزمنة
Your skin gets more blood flow when you change your lifestyle,
جلدك يحصل على دماء أكثر عندما تغير نمط حياتك
so you age less quickly. Your skin doesn't wrinkle as much.
إذا فأنت تهرم بسرعة أقل ولا يترهل جلدك بسرعة
Your heart gets more blood flow.
قلبك يحصل على دماء أكثر
We've shown that you can actually reverse heart disease.
نرى أنك تستطيع أن تتغلب على أمراض القلب
That these clogged arteries that you see on the upper left,
تلك الشرايين المسدودة في أعلى يسار الشاشة
after only a year become measurably less clogged.
بعد سنة واحدة أصبح أقل إنسداداً بشكل ملحوظ
And the cardiac PET scan shown on the lower left,
وكذلك الأشعة في أسفل يسار الشاشة
the blue means no blood flow.
الأزرق يعني لا يوجد دم
A year later -- orange and white is maximum blood flow.
بعد سنة -- البرتقالي والأبيض هو أقصى تدفق للدم
We've shown you may be able to stop and reverse the progression
أنت كذلك تستطيع أن توقف وتعاكس التدهور
of early prostate cancer and, by extension, breast cancer,
لسرطان البنكرياس في مراحله الأولى وكذلك سرطان الثدي
simply by making these changes.
بالقيام بهذه الأشياء بكل بساطة
We've found that tumor growth in vitro was inhibited
وجدنا كذلك أن نمو الورم قد تراجع
70 percent in the group that made these changes,
في 70 بالمئة من الأشخاص الذين قاموا بهذه التغييرات
whereas only nine percent in the comparison group.
بينما كانت النسبة 9 بالمئة فقط في الأشخاص الآخرين
These differences were highly significant.
وهذا الفرق ذو أهمية كبيرة
Even your sexual organs get more blood flow,
وكذلك الجهاز التناسلي سيحصل على كمية أكبر من الدم
so you increase sexual potency.
فتزيد القدرة الجنسية
One of the most effective anti-smoking ads was done
أحد أكثر إعلانات مكافحة التدخين فعالية
by the Department of Health Services,
قامت بعمله (دائرة الخدمات الصحية)
showing that nicotine, which constricts your arteries,
تظهر النيكوتين يضيق أوعيتك الدموية
can cause a heart attack or a stroke,
من الممكن أن يسبب نوبة قلبية أو سكتة دماغية
but it also causes impotence.
وقد يسبب العجز الجنسي كذلك
Half of guys who smoke are impotent.
نصف الأشخاص المدخنين عاجزون جنسياً
How sexy is that?
إلى أي درجة يبدو ذلك مثيراً؟
Now we're also about to publish a study --
حالياً نحن على وشك نشر دراسة
the first study showing you can change gene expression in men with prostate cancer.
توضح أنه بإمكاننا أن نغير جينات شخص مصاب بسرطان البروستاتا
This is what's called a heat map --
هذا ما يسمى "خارطة الحرارة"ـ
and the different colors -- and along the side, on the right, are different genes.
وهذه الألوان المختلفة في الجانب الأيمن هي جينات مختلفة
And we found that over 500 genes were favorably changed --
وجدنا أكثر من 500 جين قابل للتغير
in effect, turning on the good genes, the disease-preventing genes,
في الواقع تنشيط الجينات الجيدة ، تلك التي تمنع المرض
turning off the disease-promoting genes.
وإيقاف عمل الجين المسبب للمرض
And so these findings I think are really very powerful,
وهذه النتائج قوية للغاية كما أعتقد
giving many people new hope and new choices.
وتعطي العديد من الأشخاص أمل جديد وخيارات جديدة
And companies like Navigenics and DNA Direct and 23andMe,
شركات مثل نيقسجينكس وديركت دي إن إأ و23 آند مي
that are giving you your genetic profiles,
التي تعطيك خريطتك الجينية
are giving some people a sense of, "Gosh, well, what can I do about it?"
تعطي بعض الأشخاص إحساس بـ "ياإلهي، ماذا يمكنني العمل حيال ذلك؟"ـ
Well, our genes are not our fate, and if we make these changes --
حسناً ، جيناتنا ليست قدرنا ، إذا قمنا بعمل هذه التغييرات
they're a predisposition -- but if we make bigger changes
سيكون هناك إستعداد ، ولكن إذا قمنا بتغييرات أكبر
than we might have made otherwise,
من الممكن أن نجعلها تختلف
we can actually change how our genes are expressed.
نستطيع أن نغير طريقة عرض جيناتنا
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)